this is okay that's it that's the key
this is the important thing the human
beings are obligate tribal okay so we
are we are part of something yes and so
for if we're not part of something we
are drift yes and what's happening is is
that as we as you as you exit is you
take the red plate as you exit the the
tradition that is not working you you
now are addressed and and to the degree
to which you're able to find something
that you can be part of that is itself
has the at least the ingredients to be
adapted it may actually not initially be
adapted but it has the ingredients the
capacity has the scope and competence to
actually be able to start making
effective choices in the context of
what's happening you will naturally
begin to up gradient in that direction
so okay how's that show up mmm I had
like all right right sure to check it
out
where was this something happens
somewhere where there was a crisis there
was a town and in the town you had a
political structure and oh it was during
Katrina so Mississippi Katrina right the
you know hurricane his the leaders are
breaking and the existing political
structure just drops them all right
right what happens is this one guy who's
like the guy who runs the general store
has his shit together and he starts to
coordinate coordinate effective choices
we're talking about local small-scale
effective choices but that creates an
attractor and other people who swiftness
that attractor they're like looking and
they're seeing chaos in all directions
and they see one spot over there there's
not chaos in all directions and they
begin to orient themselves towards that
and so he says okay well you do this and
they start doing that and as it turns
out that doesn't fuck that doesn't suck
it works a little bit and and by the way
been working with him it works better so
then the zone of coordinated action the
zone of order the zone of non chaos
begins to grow organically because we
were that obligate tribalism is that if
we don't as individuals lunar lose our
capacity as individuals to see and
orient
towards what is truly effective choice
in our context as long as we have that
capacity which is our natural human
mobility and then we have the capacity
to orient ourselves to it in a flexible
way so that we can upgrade e'en its
capacity then you get a positive
feedback loop in the environment that
you that you're in my source is that
liminal shamanic um you know we're
dealing with chaos all the time really
and so let's actually use that skill set
to Rico here something that is leaps all
over it you know crosses the chasm you
know does the valley crossing into
something that works right yeah this
feels like this is a little bit of a
prophecy I mean I think what we're about
to witness is that I think we're about
to witness in the West is a generalised
failure of traditions institutional
structures leadership as it currently
exists for reasons both of corruption
and ontological epistemological
inadequacy right and the movement
towards the collective intelligence to
move it towards distributed intelligence
cognition binding those individuals and
groups that are actually able to make
increasingly effective choices in the
context what's really happening and then
learning how to Rico here and we
coordinate with those groups so that
they were able to scale and increase
their effectiveness I would say is if
not this time and I think this time is a
good opportunity like it's a good trial
run and it may be the one where that
happens if not this time it will be sort
of in the next few times of this you
know this increase in Delta II mmm-hmm
it was a human know of course our good
but there is a problem I see in that I
mean that your prophecy I think your
prophecy is accurate what I meant is I'm
thinking again of other example the
Weimar Republic uh-huh it you get an in
it you get a group of individuals who
are locally very effective but it turns
out that the global solution that
they're proposing is actually while it
ends up destroying Germany right it
actually turns out to be massively
self-destructive
yeah the the so you clearly have
individuals that are on the street right
and in in you know in the marketplace of
Germany like they're there they're there
creating that attractor of order that's
well that's why they succeed right there
but what they do is that that particular
configuration the dynamical system they
engendered I mean this is kind of you
know a version of the tragedy of the
Commons right it's locally order
generating but what it it's it's in the
service again of this growth of a
psychotic conspiracy theory that
ultimately puts the whole you know the
whole country on a path of
self-destruction yeah I think well I
think what we're gonna see is we're
gonna see something like a million Nazi
parties oh right I think I think we're
gonna see is just lots and lots and lots
of micro psychotic cabal's yes and the
question is going to be how do they
relate to each other because and the
level of systemic breakdown is is you
know the the the default state is
failure yeah so it's not like we needed
Nazis to fail it's more like we need
something we need to do the opposite of
Nazis to succeed and the default state
is failure right so what does that look
like well it looks a little bit like
what Peter a cultural or two dot oh yeah
yeah but but x yeah multiplied by a
factor probably five orders of magnitude
oh yeah so my concern there is then you
you get you get general systems collapse
because if you get this proliferation
look at all the your internal social
environment becomes as complex and
unmanned it as unmanageable as the
external environment you're trying to
respond to wow you know it's interesting
in this case like something like a virus
and here specifically nature may be our
saving grace hmm because if the if the
if the complexity is happening higher in
the human social stack
no politics finance it's like sociology
things like identity and the medics
torture those are so easily how do I say
this
the next or amenable to psychosis
mmm-hmm
as long as I can tell a locally
effective stories that kind of makes me
feel like I'm making sense of my
environment I think I can kind of go
forward until I bump into something
nature doesn't give a fuck if my story
is that it's funny I think it just
happened actually in Iran a cleric you
went to go admitted minister some people
who have got the virus and he didn't
take any precautions because his his his
model was that he would be protected and
he got sick and died this isn't clear
what your psychotic story is like that
is that's rock-bottom this that I kind
of break it hits rock bottom and so you
know not being sick we're not dying from
sickness is like the kind that's like
that that's it wow I forgotten about
that it's acute to check some of this
whole story is is nature now at the end
of the day we're all running psychotic
narratives the questions are they
adaptive psychotic narratives or not
right right so the more the crisis is
that we run into our non sociological
crises that are affect national actual
natural crises that are visceral so you
know climate change unfortunately until
it is so intense that it's irrelevant
it's not visceral you kind of everything
you're seeing is mediated by a very
large interpretive distance and so you
can always run a narrative in between
those two points yes and avoid avoid we
call it rock bottom yeah in to hit you
in the face with something that you
can't avoid no matter what there was
something like getting sick and dying
from a virus that's growing very rapidly
you know if you take a look at it every
one of these micro cabal's of psycho
psychotics they're gonna get sick if
this is real if this is or if there's a
real thing where specifically their
local adaptiveness will be somewhat
obviously
less than others now what you're about
to say I think it's certainly come to my
mind is they you know hardcore prepper
communities are going to be
indistinguishable from groups are
actually making effective choices you
know in a larger context like there's a
whole bunch of nodes
there's whole bunch of solutions to this
particular event that are probably
equivalent in terms of their
adaptiveness unless think that it's
really big right and so it's weird like
it's one of these things where I'm
noticing as I'm talking about it would
actually maybe be best for us if this is
a bigger thing then it seems like it
might be because it would be a enough
felt reality that it would push our
consciousness past certain black holes
that were in right now so more like the
Bronze Age collapse yeah which open
battle right you get this PC ation of
all these news you know cultural
economic political forms of organization
and cognition changes fundamentally yeah
in fact of you see if you think about it
I could be thinking okay so we can go up
you can say then the Chinese went
through that kind of dynamic what seven
times like every every dynasty has gone
through a collapse that was on the order
of like two-thirds mortality right in a
couple hundred years of chaos and then
that gave rise to the next dynasty it's
funny because the continuity of China
which is different than the
discontinuity of the Bronze Age I think
is precisely that more term attitude
know we've got some sixty percent to
seventy five percent or something like
that you probably have no longer China
to China you have something which is you
know the Hittites
to the Greeks yeah and then on the so
then you've got like some Bronze Age
collapse the Chinese collapse the Roman
collapse and then like the Black Plague
something like that or the black plague
awful as it was didn't really interrupt
the continuity of the West
it created a real the the thing that
came out the other end was very very
different but I would say and deeply
fundamentally was still still thought of
itself as the West at least yeah yeah
there's a continuity of I there's a
certain continuity of identity back
beyond it yeah
yeah so this is you do the map all the
way back down to the individual so if
you've got somebody who's got your
delusion or an addiction it's theirs how
hard do you have to hit rock bottom to
have your moment of clarity and that's
the question and ideally you don't have
to hit too hard the softer you can hit
it's the moment of clarity you're
looking for it's not the rock bottom
you're looking for yeah yeah and I guess
that's the question is how hard do we
have to hit rock bottom to have an a
moment of clarity adequate to the amount
of change that we need to make in our
interior and our exterior to be truly
adapted to the context that we're
finding ourselves in that's a good
question